<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
  <title>Understanding Term Rewriting</title>

  <section>
    <title>Motivation and introduction</title>

    <para>Many forms of simplification or symbolic manipulation can be
    expressed by <emphasis>term rewriting</emphasis>. Recall the
    simplification rule</para>

    <para><programlisting>(<emphasis>a</emphasis> + <emphasis>b</emphasis>)<superscript>2</superscript> = <emphasis>a</emphasis><superscript>2</superscript> + 2<emphasis>ab</emphasis> + <emphasis>b</emphasis><superscript>2</superscript></programlisting>from
    high school algebra or the rule to calculate the derivative of the sum of
    two functions <emphasis>u</emphasis> and <emphasis>v</emphasis>:</para>

    <programlisting>d(<emphasis>u</emphasis> + <emphasis>v</emphasis>)/d<emphasis>x</emphasis> = d<emphasis>u</emphasis>/d<emphasis>x</emphasis> + d<emphasis>v</emphasis>/d<emphasis>x</emphasis></programlisting>

    <para>In both cases, there is a complex <emphasis>left-hand
    side</emphasis> that can be simplified into the expression appearing at
    the <emphasis>right-hand side</emphasis>. These expressions are called
    <emphasis>term</emphasis>s and this explains the name <emphasis>term
    rewriting</emphasis>. The precise form of such a term may differ and is
    explained below. Observe that some of the items on the left-hand side
    re-appear at the right-hand side (e.g., <emphasis>a</emphasis>,
    <emphasis>b</emphasis>, <emphasis>u</emphasis>, <emphasis>v</emphasis>);
    they are called <emphasis>variables</emphasis> and are used during the
    simplification.</para>

    <para>In order to apply such a simplifcation rule (or better:
    <emphasis>rewrite rule</emphasis>), several ingredients play a
    role:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>an initial expression (a term) that is to be simplified.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>a subexpression where the rule might be applied (this is called
        the <emphasis>redex</emphasis>); there must be a
        <emphasis>match</emphasis>, between the redex and the left-hand side
        of the rule we want to apply; finding a match means that we can find
        values for the variables in the left-hand side of the rule that make
        the left-hand side and the redex identical.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>next, the redex in the initial expression is replaced by the
        right-hand side of the rule, after replacing the variables by the
        values found during the match.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Term rewriting is a simplification process that starts with one or
    more rewrite rules and an initial term. This initial term is gradually
    reduced to a term that cannot be further simplified: this is the outcome
    of the rewriting process and is called the <emphasis>normal
    form</emphasis>.</para>

    <para>In each step, a redex is searched for in (the possibly already
    simplified) initial term and it is replaced by the rewrite rule that can
    be applied.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Terms</title>

    <para></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Matching</title>

    <para></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Examples</title>

    <para></para>
  </section>
</article>