<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Simplified DocBook XML V1.0//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/simple/1.0/sdocbook.dtd">
<article>
  <title>Version management in the Meta-Environment</title>

  <authorblurb>
    <para>Gerco Ballintijn</para>

    <para>Jurgen Vinju</para>
  </authorblurb>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>One can use a version management system in different ways. This
    document describes our methods concerning checkout, commits, branching,
    and tool support. The standard version control system is Subversion. The
    reader of this text is therefore expected to understand Subversion
    concepts:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Repositories</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Working copies</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Revisions</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Tags and branches</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The following links provide ample documentation on these
    subjects:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><ulink
        url="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/nightly/en/svn-book.html">Subversion
        manual</ulink></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink
        url="http://www.cwi.nl/htbin/www-cst/Twiki/view/Cst/ServerServiceSVN">CWI
        subversion server online documentation</ulink></para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Goals</title>

    <para>The Meta-Environment development team has two overall version
    management goals:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>To always have a reasonably up-to-date version available of the
        Meta-Environment software of production quality.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>To allow developers as much freedom to experiment as
        possible</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The version management policies and mechanisms described here, were
    chosen specifically to support these two goals.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Overview</title>

    <para>The Meta-Environment consists of between 40 and 60 packages. These
    packages are managed using the Subversion version management system,
    stored in a single repositories located at:</para>

    <para>svn+ssh://svn.cwi.nl/ To manage packages, the developers use the
    Subversion trunk, branch, and tags concepts. Since every package is
    individually version-managed, every package has its own trunk, zero or
    more branches, and zero or more tags. To achieve the first goal, the
    version of the code on the trunk should be kept stable, that is, the trunk
    should always store a reasonably up-to-date version of the package of
    production quality. It is the responsibility of every developer not to
    "break the code" on the trunk. The GLT development team distinguishes two
    types of changes:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Low-impact: changes that do NOT threaten the stability of
        code.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>High-impact: changes that threaten the stability of the
        code.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Low-impact changes are trivial changes, such as the correction of
    typo's, and can be commit directly to the trunk. High-impact changes are
    basically all other, non-trivial changes. Since non-trivial changes
    threaten the stability of the code and the code on the trunk has to remain
    stable, all non-trivial changes require some form of consultation, peer
    review, and testing before being integrated into the trunk. The use of
    branches facilitates these activities since they allow version management
    for these changes, such as intermediate commits and rollbacks, independent
    of code on the trunk. Branches also allow version management for
    experiments, even if these experiments will not be integrated into the
    trunk, thus facilitating the second goal. The GLT team also uses a
    separate form of branches, called release branches, that facilitate
    maintenance on previously released code. As a consequence, the GLT team
    recognizes the following four types of branches:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The trunk (i.e., the integration branch)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Developmental branches</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Experimental branches</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Release branches</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Migration from CVS to Subversion</title>

    <para>On May 12th 2006, we have migrated the GLT modules from two CVS
    repositories, located at CWI and INRIA, to a single Subversion repository,
    located at CWI. Because of this migration, the cvsmerge script has lost
    its purpose. Instead you should use the SvnMerge script ("svnmerge")
    provided with the Subversion source. </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Development branches</title>

    <para>To protect the stability of the trunk, a developer should always
    create a branch for an intended change, unless he is sure the change is
    trivial. When the development effort has resulted in stable code on the
    branch, the changes can be integrated (merged) into the trunk. The trunk
    should thus be considered the "integration branch" for the next release.
    This way of working is described by the mainline and task-branch SCM
    patterns. To prevent developmental and experimental branches from
    diverging (too much) from the trunk, developers should use the SvnMerge
    script to incorporate (merge) concurrent changes on the trunk into their
    branch. By using the script to stay up-to-date, merging changes back into
    the trunk becomes much easier because the process of resolving merge
    conflicts is spread over time.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Release branches</title>

    <para>A second source of branches is the release process. Every time a
    package is released, a branch is created for this release. All bug fixes
    for the released package are performed on this branch, and when desired
    foreward ported (e.g., merged) to the trunk. Release branches are never
    merged with the trunk. The process of forward porting changes on the
    release branch to the trunk is NOT supported by the SvnMerge
    script.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>ChangeLog entries</title>

    <para>Each package has a ChangeLog file in its root directory that records
    all (important) changes to the package. The ChangeLog file consists of
    entries that provide a description of the change, including the date of
    the change, and that are sorted last change first. This change information
    can then be used, for instance, during debugging. When working on a
    branch, however, recording changes in the ChangeLog file requires special
    attention. The problem with the ChangeLog file occurs when changes (and
    their entries) are imported from the trunk. Since these changes have
    occured concurrently on the trunk and other branches, their dates overlap,
    and consequently their entries should be interleaved in the ChangeLog
    file. Interleaving the change information like this is, however,
    confusing. The solution to this problem is to use a separate ChangeLog
    file per branch (e.g., ChangeLog.&lt;branch-name&gt;) and record all
    changes on the branch in this file. This file is added to the branch and
    grows with every commit. Change entries from imported changes would still
    simply be added to the normal ChangeLog file. When work on the branch has
    completed and the changes can be integrated back into the trunk (i.e.,
    "integration branch"), two extra steps are needed. The first step is that
    after the "svn merge" command (but before the associated commit), an entry
    is added to the ChangeLog file, which summarizes the whole
    ChangeLog.&lt;branch-name&gt;. The second step is the removal of the file
    ChangeLog.&lt;branch-name&gt;, that is, the file is not added/commited to
    the trunk.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>The use of the SvnMerge script</title>

    <section>
      <title>Background</title>

      <para>The svnmerge script simplifies the use of branches using the
      mainline and task branch SCM patterns. In these usage patterns, the
      Subversion trunk is a stable code line where all new features and bug
      fixes eventually end up, that is, the trunk is the integration branch.
      For trivial changes, a developer can simply checkout the trunk and
      commit its changes directly to the trunk. For changes that have a larger
      impact and require a longer development effort (the usual case),
      branches allow independent parallel development with the possibility to
      commit intermediate changes to the branch. These branches (and their
      associated working copies) can be kept up-to-date with the trunk using
      the svnmerge script. Further information can be found at: </para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><ulink
          url="http://www.dellroad.org/svnmerge/index">http://www.dellroad.org/svnmerge/index</ulink></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><ulink
          url="http://www.sipfoundry.org/tools/svnmerge.html">http://www.sipfoundry.org/tools/svnmerge.html</ulink></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Generated commit message</title>

      <para>To ease the writing of correct commit messages the SvnMerge script
      creates its own commit message, per default in the file
      svnmerge-commit-message.txt. This file can be read, and edited if
      needed, during the svn commit.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title> Differences between CvsMerge and SvnMerge</title>

      <para>The following table describes some difference between the use of
      cvsmerge and svnmerge. Options and arguments for CvsMerge and SvnMerge
      have been left out. Unlike the CvsMerge script, the SvnMerge operations
      are all started from the working copy of the branch. It is preferable to
      give the trunk location explicitly with svnmerge init since svnmerge
      sometimes computes the wrong location.</para>

      <informaltable>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">Task</emphasis></entry>

              <entry><emphasis role="bold">CVS
              implementation</emphasis></entry>

              <entry><emphasis role="bold">Subversion
              implementation</emphasis></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Start a branch</entry>

              <entry>cvsmerge begin-branch</entry>

              <entry>svn copy svnmerge init svn commit</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Track changes</entry>

              <entry>(not available)</entry>

              <entry>svnmerge avail</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Merge changes</entry>

              <entry>cvsmerge import-from-trunk cvs commit</entry>

              <entry>svnmerge merge svn commit</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Revert changes</entry>

              <entry>rm cvs update cvsmerge reset-import </entry>

              <entry>svn revert (or) cd ..; rm -rf</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>End a branch</entry>

              <entry>cvsmerge end-branch cvs commit</entry>

              <entry>svn merge svn commit</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>

      <para> </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Example 1: Start a Branch</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>svn checkout svn+ssh://svn.cwi.nl/aterm/trunk aterm</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>cd aterm</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>svn copy . svn+ssh://svn.cwi.nl/aterm/branches/example</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>svn switch svn+ssh://svn.cwi.nl/aterm/branches/example</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>svnmerge init svn+ssh://svn.cwi.nl/aterm/trunk</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>svn propget svnmerge-integrated . # check the source and
          revision information</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>svn commit</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Example 2: Work on Branch</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>svnmerge avail # check which revisions are available</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>svnmerge avail -l # check their commit messages</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>svnmerge avail -d # check their differences</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>svnmerge merge -r18694 # merge in a specific revision</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>[... deal with possible conflicts created by svnmerge
          ...]</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>[... edit ChangeLog file for this branch ...]</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>svn commit</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Example 3: End a Branch</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>svn checkout svn+ssh://svn.cwi.nl/aterm/trunk aterm</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>cd aterm</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>svn merge svn+ssh://svn.cwi.nl/aterm/trunk
          svn+ssh://svn.cwi.nl/aterm/branches/example</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>[... deal with possible conflicts created by svn ...]</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>[... edit the ChangeLog file, merge it with the ChangeLog file
          local for the branch manually and consistently ...]</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>svn propdel svnmerge-integrated . # not needed on the
          trunk</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>svn commit</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Document TODO's</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Examples of high- and low-impact (risk) changes</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>More explicitly mention the possibility, use, and value of
        delayed integration of changes (branches)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Splitting up a specific package needs to be explained</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Explicitly mention with new packages</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</article>